BUILTIN Variables are defined in capital letters.
Variable Declaration:name = Mark  ;echo ${name}; output:Mark
I/p multiple variables from keyboard:  echo"Enter names : "
read name1 name2 name3 
echo "Enterd names : $name1"
To extract i/p as an array: read -a names
Convert arguments to an array: args=("$@")
No. of args : echo $#
echo -e "Enter the name of the file : \c" : \c keeps the cursor in the same line and -e is used for enabling \c
In file test operators:
-e : if file exists or not
-f : if regular file exists or not
-d : if directory exists or not
-b : for block special files
video ,music,image files are block special files.
scale is used to get decimal result of divison operator.
For configuring network system(servers) using shell script,enter the network details by editing vagrantfile.
to know the open ports: netstat -nutl
to remove directory along with contents: rm -r directory_name
lsblk : it lists info for block devices.
lscpu : it gives info about cpu
lsmem : gives memory info
uname -r : gives kernel --version info
runlevel : it shows the system should login after boot ,5 : for GUI(graphical target) ,3: for CLI(multi user target)
to see default target : systemctl get-default
to change default target: systemctl set-default target_name
df -hP : gives detail of all the mounted syatem
sudo ls -l /sbin/init : to know thw init process used by system
lshw : to know hardware details of the system.
set nu : gives line number in vi script